<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>

<!--
  Copyright 2014 by Citrix Systems, Inc.  Created by Gordon Stretch <Gordon.Stretch@citrix.com>. This work is licensed under the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/.
-->


<!DOCTYPE book PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../../../../doctools/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"[
  <!ENTITY % local SYSTEM "../local.ent"> 
   %local;
]>
<book lang="en" id="installation_guide">
 <bookinfo id="bookinfo_titlestuff">
  <title>User Guide</title>
  <subtitle>&COMPANY_NAME_SHORT; &PRODUCT_BRAND; &PRODUCT_VERSION;</subtitle>
  <pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="B Y"?></pubdate>
  
  <copyright>
   <year><?dbtimestamp format="Y"?></year>
  </copyright>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/XenClient.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>
  	
 </bookinfo>
 
 <chapter>
  <title>Introducing &PRODUCT_BRAND;</title>
  
  <para>
   Thank you for choosing &PRODUCT_BRAND;<trademark class="trade"/> from
   &COMPANY_NAME_LEGAL;
  </para>
  <para>&PB; is a bare-metal hypervisor that uses native hardware
   support for virtualization to enable near bare-metal performance. 3D
   graphics and multimedia performance is not compromised. The hypervisor
   component of the &PB; platform is a thin layer, just a few megabytes in
   size.
  </para>

  <para>&PB; allows users to have a personal desktop image that is totally
   separated and completely isolated from a locked down corporate desktop
   image running on the same machine. The personal desktop gives the user
   the ability to install their own applications, while the corporate
   desktop image remains securely isolated and locked down, which results
   in a lower cost of operation and IT being able to provide higher
   service levels to their customers.
  </para>
  <para>&BACKEND; provides VM imaging services to &PB;. It allows users to
   pull imaged VMs on to their &PB;-enabled machines, and also to sync
   their VMs back to &BACKEND;.
  </para>
  <para>&PORTICA; technology allows users to access applications running
   in VMs other than that in which they are currently working.
  </para>
  
 </chapter>



 <chapter>
  <title>Introduction</title>
  
  <para>The &PB; software stack consists of four parts:</para>
  
  <itemizedlist>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>&PB;</emphasis> is a bare metal hypervisor that allows you
     to run multiple operating systems on a computer simultaneously.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>&BACKEND;</emphasis> provisions, backs up and manages
     virtual machine (VM) images.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>&DAZZLE;</emphasis> is an self-service application store.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     <emphasis>&PORTICA;</emphasis> allows application windows to be
     shared between VMs running on the same computer.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
  </itemizedlist>
  
  <para>Together, &PB;, &BACKEND;, &DAZZLE; and &PORTICA; provide the
   capacity to radically simplify the deployment and maintenance of
   desktops and applications to users in a way that provides secure
   computing and ease of use for users and administrators alike. By
   enabling multiple operating systems to be installed on a single
   computer and providing the ability to switch between running operating
   systems in real-time, a user can be provided with a single computer for
   both home and office use, with each operating system securely isolated
   from the other. Additionally, user data can be separated from
   system data, and the system data refreshed on a regular basis, ensuring
   the speed and great user experience of a fresh installation each day,
   and ease of patch deployment and operating system updates. &PB; differs
   from many other desktop virtualization schemes by preserving the graphics
   performance of the virtual machine most commonly used.
  </para>
  
  <para>When it comes to applications, &PB; integrates with &DAZZLE; to
   allow users to pull the applications they want onto their computers
   without any intervention by systems administrators. The user can also
   leverage &PORTICA; to seamlessly share application windows between
   operating systems.
  </para>
  
  <para>In short, &PB; and related technologies provide a safe, secure and
   simple way to provision and maintain applications and operating systems
   in the enterprise in a manner that combines maximum performance, cost
   effectiveness and ease of use.
  </para>
  
  
  
  <section>
   <title>&PB;</title>
   
   <para>The &PB; software is based on bare-metal virtualization. It can
    be thought of as a software layer that acts as an intermediary between
    the operating systems (sometimes referred to as virtual machines or
    VMs) running on it and the physical hardware. This allows the user to
    run multiple VMs on a single computer simultaneously, and switch
    between them in real time. The operating systems are isolated from
    eachother, ensuring that a malicious piece of software that might
    infect one VM will not be able to infect any other VMs.
   </para>
   
   <para>The hypervisor layer controls the resources of the physical
    machine (RAM, GPU, disk, and so on) so that all of the available
    computing power is made available to the VM that the user is currently
    using. This results in barely measurable performance impact. 
   </para>
   
   <para>&PB; management capabilities are provided by &BRAND_CONSOLE;. The
    &BRAND_CONSOLE; user interface is displayed after the &PB; software
    has been installed and the computer has rebooted. &BRAND_CONSOLE;
    guides the user or systems administrator through the process of
    installing VMs, either using physical vendor media or by downloading
    an image that a systems administrator has assigned to them using
    &BACKEND;. &BRAND_CONSOLE; also provides an easy to use network
    configuration utility and the ability to start, stop and suspend VMs,
    and interact with &BACKEND;.
   </para>
   
   <para>Once the user has installed the VMs they want to run on their
    computer and started them, switching between running VMs is as easy as
    using a keystroke (for example, 
    <keycap>
     Ctrl+<replaceable>2</replaceable>
    </keycap>
    )or using the switcher bar, which appears when the
    user hovers the mouse in the middle of the top of the screen. Other
    than that, the user experience is almost precisely the same as running
    a single operating system.
   </para>


     <!-- FIXME: needs to be somewhere else -->
     <para>&HDX; is a performance enhancement to permit a VM to avoid the
      overhead of virtualization for the graphics system.</para> 
     <para>
      At any given time, only one VM running on a machine can enjoy
      HDX 3D Graphics acceleration.
       If multiple VMs are enabled to use HDX 3D Graphics,
      only the first enabled VM started after the machine is booted
      will enjoy HDX 3D Graphics acceleration.  </para> <note>
      <para>&HDX; will only be available once the &PV_TOOLS; have been
      installed on the VM.  </para> </note> 
   
   <section>
    <title>&PB; networking</title>
    
    <para>The XenClient platform allows the user to configure the wired
     network mode for each virtual machine independently. The preferred
     choice depends on network topology and user environment. Wireless
     connections will always be <literal>Shared Mode</literal>. The rest
     of this section presents the various networking modes.
    </para>
    
    <section>
     <title>Shared Mode</title>
     
     <para>
      By default all network connections are set to <literal>Shared Mode</literal>. The internal &PB; network architecture uses network address translation (NAT) to allow all virtual machines to share a single external wired or wireless network connection. Wired connections are allocated an IP address in the <literal>
       172.16.25.<replaceable>x</replaceable>
      </literal>
      range.  Wired connections are allocated an IP address in the <literal>
       172.16.26.<replaceable>x</replaceable> range. 
      </literal>
     </para>
     
    </section>
    
    <section>
     <title>Bridged Mode (Wired Network Connections only)</title>
     
     <para>Bridged Network Connections will expose the virtual network
      interfaces on individual VMs to the physical Ethernet, allowing them
      to acquire an external IP Address from the network. Bridged mode is
      suitable in situations where you want to allow external systems to
      directly access services such as file or printer sharing within your
      virtual machine.
     </para>
     
     <note>
      <para>Bridged mode requires that each virtual NIC be configured
       appropriately. Either the physical network will have to provide
       DHCP to allow the interface to establish an IP address and
       associated configuration, or you will need to statically configure
       the network settings on that interface from within the virtual
       machine.
      </para>
     </note>
     
     
     
    </section>
    
    <section>
     <title>Internal</title>
     
     <para>Internal Mode only allows network communication between VMs.</para>
    </section>
    
   </section>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>&BACKEND;</title>
   
   <para>&BACKEND; manages and provisions VM images, called Desktops.
    Once a &PB; computer has registered with &BACKEND; users may:
   </para>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>Download VM images assigned to them by an administrator.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>Upload a VM on their computer to &BACKEND;</para>
    </listitem>

    <listitem>
     <para>Register it to be managed by &BACKEND;.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>Backup their user data.</para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>Receive regular system partition refreshes.</para>
    </listitem>
    
   </itemizedlist>
   

    <para>When a VM is registered with &BACKEND; as a managed appliance a
     copy of the original VM is created and made available for use in
     &BC;. The original VM may still be used but will not have any
     relationship with &BACKEND;.
    </para>

   
   <para>A system administrator can use &BACKEND; to manage users, their
    desktops  and
    devices.
   </para>
   
  </section>
  

  <!-- diagram visual aid -->
  <section>
   <title>&PORTICA; overview</title>
   
   <para>&PORTICA; enables a user to share application windows seamlessly
    between running Windows operating systems. Seamless application
    sharing between VMs is achieved using the proprietary
    &COMPANY_NAME_SHORT; ICA protocol. To enable seamless application
    sharing, the <guilabel>&PB; Seamless Application Sharing</guilabel>
    software must be installed on the VM that is going to share the
    application. Support for this software is included in the &PV_TOOLS;. 
    Applications in the VM will be published through &DAZZLE;. See
    <xref linkend="dazzle_portica" />
     for more details.
   </para>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>&DAZZLE; overview</title>
   
   <para>&DAZZLE; provides users with self-service access to the
    applications and desktops they need to work productively. The
    easy-to-use &DAZZLE; interface allows users to subscribe to
    applications and desktops hosted on other &PB; VMs, XenApp and
    XenDesktop servers with a single click. Applications can be delivered
    to users in one of three ways. They can be:
   </para>
   
   <itemizedlist>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Streamed</emphasis> to the user computer and installed so
      that it can be used when the user is offline.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Accessed online</emphasis> from XenApp or XenDesktop
      resources.
     </para>
    </listitem>
     
    
    <listitem>
     <para>
      <emphasis>Locally installed</emphasis> and shared between VMs. In
      this case the application will be monitored when the user is online
      and reinstalled if the application gets corrupted or the systems
      administrator provides an updated version.
     </para>
    </listitem>
     
    
   </itemizedlist>

   <!-- FIXME reword with extreme prejudice -->

   <para>In all cases an application shortcut is placed on the user
    desktop or windows <guilabel>Start</guilabel> menu which starts an ICA
    session when double-clicked, causing the application to appear
    integrated on the user desktop.
   </para>
   
   <para>For added security, although the application is shared, when an
    application is in focus the keystrokes and mouse movements are
    forwarded directly to the &PB; hypervisor and so that the VM that is
    displaying the application is never aware of them. 
    
   </para>
   
  </section>
  
 </chapter>


 <chapter id="sys_requirements">
  <title>System Requirements</title>
  <section>
   <title>Hardware requirements</title>
   <para>&PB; runs on 64bit platforms only. The hardware requirements are:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Intel Core 2 Duo Processor
     </para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>1GB of memory (1 XP Instance) minimum</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>2GB RAM or greater recommended</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>160GB disk space or greater recommended</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Intel Integrated Graphics 400MHD</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Management - Intel vPro</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Supported operating systems</title>
   <para>Supported operating systems are:</para>
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Microsoft Windows XP 32bit SP3</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Microsoft Windows Vista 32bit SP2</para>
    </listitem>
    <listitem>
     <para>Microsoft Windows 7</para>
    </listitem>
   </itemizedlist>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>Supported laptop models</title>
   <informaltable>
    <tgroup cols='8'>
     <colspec colwidth='0.75in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='0.75in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='0.55in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='1in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='0.75in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='1in'/>
     <colspec colwidth='0.75in'/>
     
     <thead><row>
       <entry>
        <para>Vendor</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Product</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Type</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>WiFi</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Graphic</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>CPU</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Chipset</para>
       </entry>
       
      </row>
     </thead>
     
     <tbody>
      
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>Dell</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Latitude</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>E4300</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Dell Wireless 1397,
         Dell Wireless 1510,
         Intel WiFi 5100,
         Intel WiFi 5300
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GM45</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel Centrino 2</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GS45 Express Chipset</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
      
      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>Dell</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Latitude</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>E6400</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Dell Wireless 1397,
         Dell Wireless 1510,
         Intel WiFi 5100,
         Intel WiFi 5300
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GM45</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel Centrino 2</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel 45 Express Chipset</para>
       </entry>
      </row>
            

      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>HP</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Elite Book</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>6930p</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel WiFi 5300,
         Broadcom 4322AGN
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GM45</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel Centrino 2</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GM45 Express Chipset</para>
       </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>HP</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>2530p</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>Lenovo</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Think Pad</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>T400</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel WiFi 5100,
         Intel WiFi 5300,
         Intel WiFi 5350
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel GM45</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel Centrino 2</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>Intel 45 Express Chipset</para>
       </entry>
      </row>

      <row>
       <entry>
        <para>Lenovo</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>X200</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD
        </para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
       <entry>
        <para>TBD</para>
       </entry>
      </row>

     </tbody>
    </tgroup>
   </informaltable>
  </section>
 </chapter>
 <chapter>
  <title>Installation Overview</title>
  <para>To install &PB; and take advantage of &PORTICA; and the &BACKEND; 
   provisioning services, perform the following steps.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Installing &PB; and related technologies</title>
   <step>
    <para>
     Install and setup &BACKEND;. See <xref linkend="install_transmitter" /> for information about how to do this.
    </para>
   </step>
   <!-- FIXME: reference env -->

   <step>
    <para>
     Install the &PB; software on one of the supported machines. See <xref linkend="installation" /> for information on how to do this. 
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>In &BC;, create a VMs with &HDX_FIRST; enabled. For information
     about how to do this, see <olink targetdoc="administration" targetptr="create_from_cd" />
     .
    </para>
   </step>
   
   <step>
    <para>In &BC; create a second VM that does not have &HDX; enabled. For
     information about how to do this, see <olink targetdoc="administration" targetptr="xc_admin" />
      for information about how to do this.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Install &PORTICA;. See <xref linkend="dazzle_portica" /> for
     information about how to do this.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
  </procedure>
 </chapter>

 <chapter id="bios">
  <title>Preparing a machine for installation</title>

  <!-- FIXME: SATA? -->

  <procedure>

   <step>
    <!-- FIXME: not just BIOS -->
    <para>Ensure that the hardware has the correct BIOS settings. To do
     this:
    </para>
    <procedure>
     <!-- FIXME: X200 -->
     <title>Preparing a Lenovo T400 for installation</title>
     <step>
      <para>Press the blue ThinkVantage button, F1 while the machine is
       booting.
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>Config > CPU > Intel Virtualisation Technology</guilabel> to <literal>
        Enabled
       </literal>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>Config > CPU > Intel VT-d feature</guilabel> to <literal>
        Enabled
       </literal>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Move the wireless switch to the rightmost position (green).</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Disable AMT on the T400.</para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure>
     <title>Preparing a Dell E6400 or E4300 for installation</title>
     <step>
      <para>Press F12, select BIOS, while the machine is booting.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>Wireless > Wi-Fi Catcher</guilabel> to <literal>
        Disabled
       </literal>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>Virtualisation Support > Virtualisation > Enable
        Intel Virtualization Technology
       </guilabel>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>Virtualisation Support > VT for Direct I/O > Enable
        VT for Direct I/O
       </guilabel>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Move the wireless switch towards the screen (red).</para>
     </step>
    </procedure>
    <procedure>

     <!-- FIXME: 2530p -->
     <title>Preparing a HP6930p for installation</title>
     <step>
      <para>Press Esc, F10, while the machine is booting.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>
       Set <guilabel>System Configuration > Device Configuration >
        Virtualization Technology > Enabled
       </guilabel>
       .
      </para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Press the WiFi icon so it changes colour from red to blue.</para>
     </step>
     <step>
      <para>Ensure that you have BIOS version F.12 or later.</para>
     </step>

    </procedure>
    <note>
    <!-- FIXME: TPM. per-model instructions -->
     <para>Disable TPM (Trusted Platform Module) and TXT (Trusted Execution Technology) for all models.</para>
    </note>
   </step>
  </procedure>

 </chapter>

 <chapter id="installation">
  <title>Installing &PB;</title>
  <section>
   <title>Installing &PB; using the installer CD</title>
   <para>
    See <olink targetptr="known_issues"  targetdoc="releasenotes" /> for
    any known issues that might affect your installation.
   </para>
   <warning>
    <para>Installing &PRODUCT_BRAND; erases the entire contents of the
     hard disk on the target system.
    </para>
   </warning>

   <para>Before beginning the installation process, please ensure that the
    machine's BIOS is correctly configured. <!-- FIXME -->
   </para>

   <para>&PB; offers two installation modes: quick installation or
    advanced installation. Use the arrow keys and the <keycap>Enter</keycap> button to navigate.
   </para>
   <procedure>
    <title>Quick Install</title>
    <step>
     <para>Boot from the &PRODUCT_BRAND; Installer CD.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Quick Install</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>OK</guilabel> and review the software license.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Exit</guilabel> and <guilabel>Yes</guilabel> to
      accept the terms of the license.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Continue</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Verify</guilabel> to ensure that the installation
      media is valid and uncorrupted, or <guilabel>Skip</guilabel> to
      begin the installation.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When the installation has completed, press <guilabel>Continue</guilabel> and then <guilabel>
       Reboot
      </guilabel>
      to reboot the machine.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>The &BRAND_CONSOLE; is displayed. You can use the UI to create
      VMs.
     </para>
     
    </step>
   </procedure>
   <procedure>
    <title>Advanced Install</title>
    <step>
     <para>Boot from the &PRODUCT_BRAND; Installer CD.</para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Advanced Install</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>OK</guilabel> and review the software license.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Exit</guilabel> and <guilabel>Yes</guilabel> to
      accept the terms of the license.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Continue</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
     Enter a password, and choose <guilabel>OK</guilabel>. Confirm the
     password (neither is displayed) and choose <guilabel>OK</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Verify</guilabel> to ensure that the installation
      media is valid and uncorrupted, or <guilabel>Skip</guilabel> to move
      to the next installation step.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      Choose <guilabel>Configure</guilabel> to enter a &BACKEND;
      activation ID, or choose <guilabel>Skip</guilabel>. Enter the full
      path to your &BACKEND; server and click <guilabel>Continue</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>
      When the installation has completed, press <guilabel>Continue</guilabel> and then <guilabel>
       Reboot
      </guilabel>
      to reboot the machine.
     </para>
    </step>
    <step>
     <para>The &BRAND_CONSOLE; is displayed.
     </para>
    </step>
   </procedure>
  </section>
  
 </chapter>

 
 <chapter id="xc_admin">
  <title>&PB; Administration</title>

  <section>
   <title>&IOVM;</title>


<!-- 
general Vm display
-->

   <section>
    <title>Machine-wide power management</title>
  </section>

   <!-- FIXME: vm opt details ctrl+0 -->


   <section>
    <title>Other &IOVM; features</title>

<!--
mac address pass through
-->

  </section>
     
  
  <section id="networking">
   <title>Networking</title>
   
   <para>
    &PB; uses the open-source <ulink url="http://projects.gnome.org/NetworkManager/">
     NetworkManager
    </ulink>
    to provide network management functionality in &BC;, which allows you
    to connect to other computers and to the internet. See <ulink url="http://www.redhat.com/magazine/003jan05/features/networkmanager/">
     the documentation
    </ulink>
    of NetworkManager for more information about setting up networking
    using NetworkManager.
   </para>
   
   <note>
    <para>Whatever networks you setup in &BC; will be made available to
     all VMs, including the Wireless network which is shared between all
     VMs using Network Address Translation (NAT).
    </para>
   </note>
   
   <procedure>
    
    <title>Configuring a wired network connection</title>

    <step>
     <para>
      NetworkManager will automatically connect to the wired network and
      acquire an IP address with DHCP when an ethernet cable is plugged in.
     </para>
    </step>
    
   </procedure>
   

   
  </section>
  </section>
 <!-- transmitter -->

 <section>
  <title>Virtual Machines</title>
 

  <section>
   <title>Installing Virtual Machines</title>
   
   <procedure id="create_from_cd">
    <title>Creating a VM from vendor media</title>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      In the &IOVM; click <guilabel>Create VM</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guilabel>Create New from Vendor Media</guilabel> button.
      The <guilabel>Create a New Virtual Machine</guilabel> wizard is
      displayed.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/createVmS1x.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>

     <para>
      Select the operating system type from the <guilabel>Type</guilabel>
      dropdown list.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Enter a short name for the VM, and optionally its
      description. Select an icon to represent the VM. The short name and
      the icon will be used to distinguish VMs in the toolbar.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Click <guilabel>Next</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/createVmS2x.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>
     <para>Choose the amount of RAM to assign to the VM. The default of 1024Mb
     is appropriate for Windows Vista and Windows 7. For Windows XP, 512Mb is
     generally adequate.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guilabel>Next</guilabel> button to go to the next step of
      the wizard.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/createVmS3x.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>
     <para>Specify the size of the virtual disk to assign to the VM.
           The actual disk space used by a virtual disk reflects how much
	   data has been written to it, and so may be considerably less
	   than the size you specify.</para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Select the wired network mode. The options are:</para>
     
     <itemizedlist>
      
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <emphasis>Bridged</emphasis> which is suitable in situations where
        you want to allow external systems to directly access services
        such as file or printer sharing within your virtual machine. The
        Virtual NIC within the VM is bridged to the physical network.
        Incoming connections to your VM are enabled.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <emphasis>Shared</emphasis> which places your Virtual NIC on a
        private network on the XenClient system and allows  outgoing
        connections using NAT (network address translation). In this case
        you will not be able to allow incoming connections to your virtual
        machine.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      
      <listitem>
       <para>
        <emphasis>Internal</emphasis> which only allows for network
        communication between VMs.
       </para>
      </listitem>
      
     </itemizedlist>
     
    </step>


    <step><para>Click <guilabel>Next</guilabel></para></step>
    
    <step>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/createVmS4x.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>
     <para>
      From the <guilabel>XenClient Tools</guilabel> menu, select 
      <guilabel>Attached</guilabel>. This causes the &PV_TOOLS; to 
      be mounted as an extra
      optical disk drive in the VM.
      This option may also be used by system integrators to attach arbitrary
      optical disk images in ISO9660 format, such as OS install disks.
     </para>
    </step>

    <step><para>If you select <guilabel>Start virtual machine automatically</guilabel>, this VM will be started automatically shortly after the &PB; platform
    boots. The VM will receive the display focus instead of the &IOVM;.
    </para>
    </step>

    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guilabel>Finish</guilabel> button.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Insert the operating system installation media into the optical
      drive of the machine.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Select the VM from the list, and
      click the <guilabel>Start</guilabel> button. If necessary, press the VM hotkey that is displayed in the UI. The VM will take focus. Complete the operating system installation as you would do on any other physical machine.
     </para>
     <note>
      <para>Do not enable automatic Windows updates until you have
       installed the &PV_TOOLS;.
      </para>
     </note>
    </step>
    
    
    
    
    
    <step>
     <para>When installation is complete, install the &PV_TOOLS; by
      running <filename>setup.exe</filename> from the
      optical disk (conventionally mounted as D:). This installs high performance virtualization aware
      drivers and an easy to use VM Switcher bar to allow switching
      between the VMs.
     </para>
    </step>

    <!-- FIXME -->    
    <step>
     <para>Download and install the latest graphics and audio drivers.</para>
    </step>

<!--

go to www.intel.com
Work | Support & Downloads
(click no on survey)
Select a Family | Grahpics
Select a Line | Laptop graphics controllers
Select a Product | Mobile Intel(r) 4 Series Express Chipset Family
Download Drivers and Software
wait for intel download center to come out of maintenance
-->

   </procedure>
  </section>

  </section>
  <section>
   <title>Using &PB; with the &BACKEND;</title>

   <para>VMs may be downloaded and uploaded to the &BACKEND;. In &PB;,  causing a VM to be uploaded is termed Publishing. Users may download managed VMs provided by the administrators of the &BACKEND;. To interact with the &BACKEND;, a &PB; instance must be Registered.
   </para>



   <!-- register with transmitter -->

<!-- 
Missing bits:
 Also a description of the Additional Options dialogue for Managed VMs would be good.
 edit vm
 publish
 connect to transmitter

Also, authors of shared images get the 'Save Changes For Reboots' checkbox; this allows changes to the system disk to be persisted across reboots; useful when installing new software.
-->
   
   <procedure>
    <title>Creating a VM from &BACKEND;</title>
    
    <para>
     See <xref linkend="transmitter" /> for information about how to make
     a VM image available to a user using &BACKEND;.
    </para>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      In &BC;, click the <guilabel>XENCLIENT</guilabel>.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guilabel>Create New VM</guilabel> button.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Click the <guilabel>Create New from Transmitter Desktop</guilabel>
      button. The <guilabel>Register with &PB; Transmitter</guilabel>
      wizard is displayed if this is the first time you have  attempted to
      create a VM using this method. Enter your activation URL and click
      the <guilabel>Next</guilabel> button.
     </para>
     
     <note>
      <para>
       See <xref linkend="transmitter" /> for the procedures to be
       performed in &BACKEND; to create an activation URL.   
      </para>
     </note>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Enter your &BACKEND; username and password and click the <guilabel>
       Next
      </guilabel>
      button.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Select a VM from the list and click the <guilabel>Next</guilabel>
      button.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>
      Provide a name for the VM and click the <guilabel>Finish</guilabel>
      button.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Wait for the VM to download. When the download has finished,
      start the VM by selecting it in the Virtual Machines list in the &IOVM; and clicking <guilabel>
       Start
      </guilabel>
      .
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>When installation is complete, install the &PV_TOOLS; by
      running <filename>setup.exe</filename> from the 
      optical disk mapped as D:. This installs high performance virtualization aware
      drivers and an easy to use VM Switcher bar to allow switching
      between the VMs.
     </para>
    </step>
    
    <step>
     <para>Download and install the latest graphics drivers.</para>
    </step>
    
    
   </procedure>
   
  </section>
  
   
 </chapter>
 
 <chapter id="dazzle_portica">
  <title>&DAZZLE; and &PORTICA;</title>


  
  <para>All applications, including those that originate from &DAZZLE;,
   can be shared seamlessly between VMs. What this amounts to in practise
   is that an application running on a VM is displayed in another VM, and
   appears and can interacted with as if it was running in that VM.
  </para>
  
  <para>From a security point of view, although the application is shared,
   keystrokes and mouse movements are forwarded directly to the &PB;
   hypervisor and the VM that is displaying the application is never aware
   of them. Also, the VM that is actually running the application is
   simply sending the graphical display via the &PB; hypervisor.
  </para>

   <warning>
    <para>Please ensure that you have installed all available Windows
     updates before installing &PORTICA;.
    </para>
   </warning>

  <procedure>
   <title>Installing &PORTICA;</title>

   <step>
    <para>Ensure that the &PV_TOOLS; are installed on each VM you wish to
     use with &PORTICA;.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Ensure that you have selected <literal>Attached</literal> for
     the <guilabel>XenClient Tools</guilabel> option in VM details, for
     the VM you wish to use to display Seamless applications.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Boot the VM if it is not already running.</para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Open the <filename>Seamless</filename> directory in the
    attached &PV_TOOLS; optical disk.</para> 
    </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click to install <filename>Receiver</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click to install <filename>CitrixOnlinePluginFull</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>
     Double-click to install <filename>Dazzle</filename>.
    </para>
   </step>

   <step>
    <para>Verify the installation by browsing the list of applications in
    the <guilabel>Dazzle Apps</guilabel> section of the Start menu.</para>
   </step>

  </procedure>
 </chapter>


 
 <chapter>
  <title>&BACKEND;</title>
  
  <para>&BACKEND; is the central backend management service that allows
   you to create virtual images, manage virtual image deployments and
   configure user access. This chapter explains the key concepts involved
   in working with &BACKEND;.
  </para>
  
  
  
  <section>
   <title>Devices</title>
   
   <para>
    A <emphasis>device</emphasis> is a computer that has the &PB;
    hypervisor installed on it. A device is registered with a &BACKEND;.
    &BACKEND; maintains asset records of the device, and 
    credentials are retained to allow secure communication between the
    device and &BACKEND;.
   </para>
   
   
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>Users</title>
   
   <para>
    A <emphasis>user</emphasis> is assigned one or more &PB;-based
    devices. &BACKEND;. A registered device is bound
    to a specific user, allowing that user to install VMs on the device.
    The system facilitates large-scale management of users and devices.
   </para>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>Desktops</title>
   
   <para>
    An <emphasis>desktop</emphasis> is a template of a VM that can be
    installed onto devices. Desktops are composed of:
   </para>
   
   
   
   <itemizedlist>
    <listitem>
     <para>Image files stored in the Microsoft Virtual Hard Disk (VHD)
      format. &PB; makes use of VHD chaining to allow VHDs to be used as 
      <emphasis>gold masters</emphasis>, where a single large VHD may 
      act as a parent to a large set of copy
      on write (CoW) children. This approach is also used to efficiently
      store subsequent versions of VM image files and backups of user
      data.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    
    <listitem>
     <para>Policy and configuration describing how the VM should act when
      it is deployed on the client device. This information includes
      details such as whether the VM is allowed to use USB devices, or
      whether it can share a unified copy and paste buffer (clipboard)
      with other VMs.
     </para>
    </listitem>
    
   </itemizedlist>
   
   <para>Desktops are versioned. &BACKEND; hosts multiple
    
    immutable versions of an desktop. New versions are generated when
    changes are made to an desktop image. An administrator can, for
    example, create a new desktop containing a simple Windows XP
    installation and publish this from &BACKEND; as version 1. They can later take the image, install some new software and release it as version 2. 
    &PB; manages deploying this update to users.
   </para>
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>Publications</title>
   
   <para>
    <emphasis>Publications</emphasis> are relationships between specific
    desktop versions and specific users or groups of users. A
    publication allows a user to instantiate a specific desktop version
    on their device. When connected to &BACKEND; users can request a list
    of available desktops, which is provided by querying for desktop
    versions that have been published to that user.
   </para>
   
   <para>By publishing specific versions of desktops to users, &PB;
    
    allows new versions to be tested on specific (small) groups of
    
    users before being widely published. This also allows updates to
    
    desktop versions to be staged across different groups of users.
   </para>
   
   <para>Using &PB; with &BACKEND; involves the four stages described
    below to create new desktop VMs, and deploy them onto client devices.
   </para>
   
   <informalfigure>
    
    <mediaobject>
     
     <imageobject>
      
      <imagedata fileref="images/transmitter_provisioning.png" width="6.02in" />
      
     </imageobject>
     
    </mediaobject>
    
   </informalfigure>
   
   <para>
    &PB; supports two types of desktops, <emphasis>private mode</emphasis>
    and <emphasis>shared mode</emphasis>. Private mode desktops are
    desktop images that are managed centrally and deployed to users, but
    the images are not updated over time. Deployed images can, however, be
    transparently backed up to &BACKEND; to ensure that data on devices
    remains protected.
   </para>
   
   <para>Shared mode desktops isolate user data from the system disk of
    the desktop VM. The system disk is reset to a known-good configuration
    on reboot. Shared mode desktops allow administrators to "patch"
    desktop VMs, installing new versions of software, for instance, and
    push these patches out to &PB; users in the background.
   </para>
   
   <para>To begin using &BACKEND;, you should first have at least one &PB;
    notebook configured, and have installed at least one desktop VM from
    vendor media that you would like to share with other &PB;-based
    notebooks in your organization. Refer to <olink targetdoc="installation" targetptr="installation" />
     for details on how to install the client software and VMs.
   </para>
   
  </section>
  
  <section>
   <title>Managing desktops using &BACKEND;</title>
   
   <para>&BACKEND; is responsible for managing the deployment of a set of
    independently authored desktop VM images (or desktops) to a large
    number of users, each with one or more &PB; devices. As devices may be
    lost or stolen, it also provides facilities to protect data (such as
    backup), and support for tracking device hardware assets that are
    owned by the organization. To achieve these goals, XenClient devices
    can operate in one of three modes: <literal>Unregistered</literal>, <literal>
     Registered
    </literal>
    ,and <literal>Bound</literal> to a specific user.
   </para>
   
   <informalfigure>
    
    <mediaobject>
     
     <imageobject>
      
      <imagedata fileref="images/transmitter_desktop_modes.png" width="5.99in" />
      
     </imageobject>
     
    </mediaobject>
    
   </informalfigure>
   
   <para>Breaking this process into three stages has a number of benefits.
    Firstly, &PB; may run as a stand-alone client virtualization
    platform in unregistered mode with no requirement to deploy a
    &BACKEND; instance.
   </para>
   
   <para>Second, registration, which allows device hardware to be tracked
    using lightweight asset-management support in &BACKEND;, can be
    performed at installation time, and is decoupled from a user
    interacting with the device. An IT administrator may then receive
    shipment of, and register, a group of new notebooks with &BACKEND; 
    before giving them out to users, and may tag the group with an invoice
    number that describes the order. In the future, this registration
    stage will be extended to allow client devices to be preloaded with
    common gold master VM images while they are connected on a high-speed
    corporate network, prior to them being given to users who may then log
    in from outside the enterprise.
   </para>
   
   <para>Finally, the binding stage of &PB; devices establishes a
    permanent link between that installation of &PB; on that piece of
    hardware, and a specific user. Once bound to a user, the &BC;
    interface will display the list of desktop VMs that have been assigned
    to that user as available for installation. VMs may be backed up to
    &BACKEND; in the background, and associated with that specific user.
    In the event that a device is lost, backups of a user's VMs may be
    used to recover their &PB; installation on a new computer.
   </para>
   
  </section>
  
 </chapter>


<!--
Should add a section about adding a new NFS Image Repository in the XT Admin UI Configuration Panel

-->

 <chapter id="install_transmitter">
  <title>Installing &BACKEND;</title>
  <para>&BACKEND; provides user and desktop provisioning services to
   &PB; users. &BACKEND; also provides a user interface for managing
   users, virtual desktops and devices.
  </para>
  <para>&BACKEND; is provided as a XenServer Virtual Appliance (XVA) file.
   &BACKEND; is based on a virtual machine template that does not require
   any installation procedures and can be imported into any XenServer 5.5
   environment. To use &BACKEND; you need to deploy a XenServer
   installation onto a new physical server. Alternately you can use an
   existing XenServer 5.5 installation.
  </para>
  <procedure>
   <title>Installing &BACKEND; on XenServer</title>
   
   <step>
    <para>Download the &BACKEND; appliance from the &COMPANY_NAME_SHORT;
     website.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>
     The compressed archive contains a <literal>.xva</literal> file.
     Uncompress the file and double-click on it to import it into
     XenCenter.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Create a new VM from the imported template by double-clicking on
     the template in XenCenter and completing the steps of the New VM
     wizard. See the XenCenter online help for assistance if required.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Configure your network to assign the IP or hostname to this
     virtual machine that you intend to be visible in URLs that will be
     used by &PB; users and administrators. By default, the system will
     use whatever numeric IP address is assigned to the host by DHCP. If
     you desire to configure your DNS to assign a hostname to the
     &BACKEND; VM, do that now.
    </para>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Once the VM is booted, log into the VM using the XenCenter
     console, with the username <literal>root</literal> and you will be
     prompted to set a password for this account. 
     The &BACKEND; installer is displayed.
    </para>
  <mediaobject>
   <imageobject>
    <imagedata fileref="images/transmitter_install.png"/>
   </imageobject>
   
  </mediaobject>


   </step>
   <step>
    <para>Configure the installer according to your environment.
     &COMPANY_NAME_SHORT; recommends that you enable mount permissions
     for the webserver user. This is enabled by default and is
     controlled the <literal>Give Mount Privileges</literal>
    </para>
    <para>The options available to you are:</para>
    <variablelist>
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Change Virtual Hostname</term>
      <listitem>
       <para>allows you to configure the hostname to be used in XenClient
        Transmitter URLs and certificates. It defaults to the systems
        numeric IP address, but may be changed at this point to be a
        textual host name.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     
     <varlistentry>
      <term>Give mount privileges</term>
      <listitem>
       <para> allows an external image repository to be configured later,
        so that Desktop VM images may be stored outside of the &BACKEND;
        VM, on an NFS server.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
     
     <varlistentry>
      <term>SSL Certificate Settings</term>
      <listitem>
       <para> allows you to generate or install an SSL certificate to be
        used by &BACKEND; for HTTPS connections.
       </para>
      </listitem>
     </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
   </step>
   <step>
    <para>When you have finished configuring the initial installation,
     select <guilabel>Perform install</guilabel> to complete the
     customization of &BACKEND; for your environment. If you quit the
     installer to inspect the VM environment, you can restart the
     installation by logging in again and running the <filename>
      /root/install.sh
     </filename>
     script.
    </para>
   </step>
  </procedure>
  <note>
   <para>For security reasons, SSH is disabled by default in the VM hosting
   the &BACKEND;. You may enable it by running <filename>/etc/init.d/ssh
     start
    </filename>
    .To persist this across reboots, run the following command as <literal>
     root
    </literal>
    :
   </para>
   <!-- FIXME: use update-rc.d! -->
   <screen>ln -s /etc/init.d/ssh /etc/rc2.d/S20ssh</screen>
  </note>
 </chapter>


 <chapter id="transmitter">
  <title>&BACKEND; Administration</title>
  
  <para>This chapter contains the procedures required for administering
   &BACKEND;, using the web-based &BACKEND; UI, which can be accessed by
   pointing a web browser at the &BACKEND; server URL. The steps involved
   in making a VM image available to a user are:
  </para>
  
  <orderedlist>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>Use a web browser to access the URL reported by
     &BACKEND; in the XenCenter console, and log in as <literal>admin</literal> with the password <literal>admin</literal>.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>In the &BACKEND; UI, create an activation ID. This ID identifies
     one or many computers. The activation ID is entered on a &PB;
     computer either during installation of when  first attempting to
     connect to &BACKEND;. &BACKEND; then automatically registers the
     computer in the &BACKEND; database.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>Create a user using the &BACKEND; interface.</para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>Use &BC; to create the VM.</para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Using &BC;, publish an existing VM to &BACKEND; by clicking the <guilabel>
      Publish Desktop
     </guilabel>
     button.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Publish Transmitter Desktop</guilabel> button,
     and log in as the user created in the first step. The VM starts to
     upload to &BACKEND;.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
   <listitem>
    <para>Once the VM upload is complete, use &BACKEND; to deploy desktop
     instances to users.
    </para>
    
    <para>Once a VM has been made available, communicate the activation
     URL to the user. The user can then use &BC; to connect to &BACKEND;
     and download the VM.
    </para>
   </listitem>
   
  </orderedlist>
  
  <procedure>
   <title>Creating a &BACKEND; activation ID</title>
   
   <para>An activation ID is required for each user to connect to
    &BACKEND; from &BC; and either access provisioned desktops or upload a
    VM image.
   </para>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     On the &BACKEND; UI <guilabel>Welcome</guilabel> tab, click <guilabel>
      Devices
     </guilabel>
     .
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guilabel>Devices</guilabel> tab, scroll down to the <guilabel>
      Device Activation Batches
     </guilabel>
     section and click <guilabel>New</guilabel>. The <guilabel>Create New
      Activation
     </guilabel>
     screen is displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>Enter an activation ID and a description. The activation ID can
     be anything.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Create and select <guilabel>Tags</guilabel> to identify this
     activation, or this batch of activations.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Create</guilabel> button.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Close</guilabel> button.
    </para>
   </step>
   
  </procedure>
  
  <procedure>
   <title>Creating a &BACKEND; user</title>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     On the &BACKEND; UI <guilabel>Welcome</guilabel> tab, click <guilabel>
      Users
     </guilabel>
     .
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guilabel>Users</guilabel> tab, click <guilabel>New</guilabel>. The <guilabel>
      Create New User
     </guilabel>
     screen is displayed.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>Enter the user details.</para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     To grant the user <literal>Administrator</literal> access check the <guilabel>
      Administrator
     </guilabel>
     checkbox.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Save</guilabel> button. The <guilabel>User
      Creation
     </guilabel>
     dialog is displayed with a status message.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Close</guilabel> button.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   
   
  </procedure>
  
  
  
  <procedure>
   <title>Assigning a desktop to a user</title>
   
   <para>
    Once a VM has been published to &BACKEND;, it is shown in the <guilabel>
     Desktops
    </guilabel>
    tab. You can now assign this desktop to users, which allows them to
    install it on their devices.
   </para>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     On the <guilabel>Desktops</guilabel> tab, use the <guilabel>Search</guilabel> box to find the desktop you want to publish, then double click it to view its details in a new tab.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Select the version to be published, and click the <guilabel>Assign</guilabel> button.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   <step>
    <para>A dialog box is displayed  with the desktop and version that you
     have selected. Choose the user that you would like to assign it to,
     and customize the configuration or policy settings.
    </para>
   </step>
   
   <step>
    <para>
     Click the <guilabel>Assign</guilabel> button to assign the desktop to
     a user. The new assignment appears in the <guilabel>Desktop
      Assignment
     </guilabel>
     table.
    </para>
   </step>
   
  </procedure>
  
  
  
 </chapter>


</book>
