<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?><!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" "../../../../doctools/docbook-xml/docbookx.dtd"[
<!ENTITY % xinclude PUBLIC "xinclude" "../../../../doctools/docbook-xml/xinclude.mod">
%xinclude;
<!ENTITY colophon PUBLIC "colophon" "../shared/colophon.ent">
<!ENTITY legal PUBLIC "legal" "../shared/legal.ent">
<!ENTITY xc_relnotes_shared PUBLIC "xc_relnotes_shared" "../shared/xc_relnotes_shared.ent">
<!ENTITY % local PUBLIC "local" "../shared/local.ent">

  %local;
]><article lang="en"><?dbhtml dir="XenClientLocalVHDCache"?>
	<articleinfo id="bookinfo_titlestuff" role="die">
		<title>&COMPANY_NAME_SHORT;<trademark class="registered"/> &PB;<trademark class="trade"/> &PRODUCT_VERSION; Local VHD Cache</title>
		<pubdate><?dbtimestamp format="d B Y"?></pubdate>
  &legal;
		<releaseinfo>&COMPANY_NAME_SHORT;<trademark class="registered"/> &PB; <trademark class="trade"/> &PRODUCT_VERSION; release.</releaseinfo>

	</articleinfo>
<?hard-pagebreak?>

	<section id="local_vhd_cache"><title>Using a Local VHD Cache to Accelerate VM Download from &BACKEND;</title>
	<para>When a VM download from &BACKEND; is initiated, &PB; attempts to locate VHDs in an attached optical disk or USB drive which would otherwise have to be downloaded from &BACKEND;. Using a local VHD cache in this manner can greatly speed up the installation of a VM image onto a device. Use the following procedure to create a local VHD cache:</para>
	
	<procedure><title>To Prepare a Local VHD Cache</title>
	
	<step><para>Create, prepare, and upload a VM to &BACKEND;.</para></step>
<!--	<step><para>Run the following command on your &BACKEND; server to enable <command>ssh</command>:</para>
	<screen>dpkg-reconfigure openssh-server</screen>
	</step> -->
	
	<step><para>To identify which VHD files are used by the VM, open the local command shell in the console on your &BACKEND; appliance, then run the following command:</para>
	<screen>get_vm_disks -n "<replaceable>vm_name</replaceable>" -v <replaceable>version</replaceable></screen>
	<note><para>Use double quotes around <replaceable>vm_name</replaceable> if it contains whitespace.</para></note>
	<para>The paths to all the VHDs associated with the specified VM are displayed.</para>
	</step>
	
	<step><para>Copy the VHDs to a USB drive or burn them to an optical disk. The USB drive must be formatted with an NTFS filesystem. For DVDs, please burn the VHDs to a UDF filesystem. Ensure that:</para>
	<itemizedlist>
	<listitem><para>The VHD filenames are not changed.</para></listitem>
	<listitem><para>The VHD files are present in the root folder of the medium.</para></listitem>


	
	</itemizedlist>
<para>It is also possible to cache a portion of a VHD file if it is too large for the cache medium. For example, if you have a 4.3 GB VHD file and a 4 GB USB drive, you can use the <command>split</command> command in a console on your &BACKEND; server:</para>
<screen>split -b 4000M <replaceable>vhd_filename</replaceable> xenclient</screen>
<para>to split the VHD into two files, <filename>xenclientaa</filename> and <filename>xenclientbb</filename>:</para>
<screen>ls -lh
total 8.6G
-rwxr-xr-x 1 hsimpson xeneng 4.3G Dec 14  2010 example.vhd
-rw-r--r-- 1 hsimpson xeneng 4.0G Jul 13 15:47 xenclientaa
-rw-r--r-- 1 hsimpson xeneng 356M Jul 13 15:48 xenclientab
</screen>
<para>You can then rename <filename>xenclientaa</filename> to <filename>example.vhd</filename> and put it on the cache medium. When a download is initiated, &PB; first searches for a USB drive that contains a portion or all of the required VHD(s), then for a optical media drive, and then that falls back to downloading any remaining VHDs or portions thereof from &BACKEND;.</para>
<note><para>For successful VHD cache reading, it is essential that the first portion of any VHD is present on the cache medium. For example, putting the <filename>xenclientab</filename> file only onto the cache medium will cause the image transfer to fail.</para></note>
	</step>
	
	<step><para>Assign the VM image to a user.</para></step>
	
	<step><para>Insert the USB device or optical disk into the user's &PB; device, and initiate the VM image download.</para></step>
	
	
	</procedure>
	
	

</section>
</article>
